Good evening and welcome to the January
14th, 2026 committee of the whole
meeting. Appreciate you all being here
in person and hopefully we have some
online. Uh tonight we're going to
discuss the proposed sixth penny
um resolution.
Uh what I'm going to do is ask the mayor
to give us a report.
I'm I'm sorry, Jennifer.
>> I just need to read the item first.
>> I know. Okay.
>> I'm just telling them what we're going
to do. Uh first thing I'm going to do is
ask the mayor to give us a report and
then I'll bring it out to the public and
allow you to make any comments. Uh once
that's done, we'll bring it back up on
the dis and then we'll discuss it. I'm
sure there's going to be some proposed
amendments. If there are, we'll put it
back out so that you can comment on
those. So that's just kind of the way
the this these committee meetings work.
It's a little bit uh
uh informal compared to a Monday night
meeting. So with that said, Jennifer,
can you read the resolution for us?
Number 17, resolution establishing the
city of Cheyenne's prioritized list of
projects proposed for potential
inclusion on the 1% specific purpose
sales tax sales and use tax ballot
proposition to be submitted to the
qualified electors of Larmy County at
the primary election on August 18th of
2026.
>> Thank you. And with that, Mr. Mayor,
could you uh give us a report, please?
>> President Crave and members of the
committee of the whole. For the record,
I'm Mayor Patrick Collins. The six penny
sales tax has had an amazing impact on
our community over the years. It's the
only funding mechanism we have to
complete large infrastructure, quality
of life, and public safety projects.
Today, we have new fire stations, an
active pavement management program, and
almost 50 miles of greenway system, a
developing downtown, and so much more
because of the investments that have
been made possible by the six penny
sales tax. The voters of Larry County
have been so awesome and so supportive.
The challenge for this ballot is that we
have more requests than projects than
the excuse me the Larmy County
commissioners have granted to the city.
We were allocated $74,250,000
and the original request we had was in
excess of $150 million. The election is
scheduled for August 18th, the date of
the primary election with early voting
starting July 2nd.
The C county commissioners have
scheduled the first meeting of the
countywide committee made up of two
members each from Pine Bluffs, Burns,
Alban, the county commission, and city
of Cheyenne for next Wednesday. They
will begin the work of putting together
the ballot that we will put forward next
summer. To give the governing body a
place to start, I have prepared a
resolution to start the discussion. And
here are some of my priorities.
5 years ago, we had aging fire stations
that were not placed in the optimal
positions due to growth of the city. In
the last six penny sales tax, the voters
approved building three new fire
stations that have helped improve
response times in our community safety.
One area that still has response time
challenges is South Cheyenne. The
growing sweetgrass, Harmony, and Meta
areas are in need of improved response
times by our fire department. That could
be accomplished by moving station two,
currently on Fox Farm Road to the land
the city's already purchased near the
corner of College Drive and South Griley
Highway. It will cover the growing areas
in the south and maximize the area that
two company can service. The request for
this is $12 million.
Again, 5 years ago, our fire
department's apparatuses were aging and
struggling with reliability. We decided
that a vehicle replacement plan was
needed to keep our mainline fire engines
current and functioning. We purchased
four engines at that time and we need to
replace three more with this ballot. You
can see our current vehicles that we're
using are 2008, 1998, and 2001. With the
lead time to order new fire engines at
four years, it makes managing our fleet
more challenging. But we hope to
purchase two fire engines and a ladder
truck at a cost of 5,23,364.
Cheyenne has a 370 mile road system
valued at close to a billion. For the
past years, we've engaged in a robust
pavement management program to stabilize
the condition of our roadways. Our city
engineer has calculated it will take at
least $10 million a year just to
stabilize our roads. The fifth penny
contributes just over 5 million to our
pavement management program, leaving a
deficit that we must make up if we want
to continue improving our roadways. I've
included $9 million in this request.
This amount is not the full request made
by our engineer. I've asked that he use
fifth penny sales tax overages that will
become available next year to make up
the difference. Maintaining our roads is
one of the highest priorities of our
residents and I hope you will maintain
this level of funding going, keep this
level of funding going. um so that we
can keep our management program moving
forward. It's more cost-effective to
maintain roads than it is to replace
them.
Our police department is asking for
technology to improve their operations.
Incar cameras have reached the end of
their lives. There's newer, better
technology, and replacing them is one of
their highest priorities. AI is also a
tool that makes a difference in law
enforcement and Chief Francisco is
asking for funding to purchase AI tools
to help with the efficiency of the
department. This $3,700,000
request includes a 5-year digital
storage plan, and I believe technology
can be a force multiplier for our or
excuse me, our police department.
Chief Dyorn is asking for some essential
equipment that he can't pay for with his
fifth penny sales tax allocation. The
fire department issues personal
protective gear to each firefighter.
This turnout gear is scheduled to be
replaced as it will reach its end of
life during the next couple of years.
And we know 90 sets of the gear will
cost $459,340.
The chief is also asking for funding to
replace 50 portable radios that will
also reach their end of life at a cost
of $599,947.
The Greenway is one of the gems of our
city. Starting in 1991, we have used the
six penny sales tax to make incremental
additions over the past 35 years. I
think we're just under 50 miles now of
paved greenway. Because we have greenway
infrastructure reaching about 35 years
old, dedicated funding for maintenance
is critical. The total request for the
greenway is $6 million split between
maintenance
and funding the incremental additions
that we will hope will keep the greenway
system growing.
In our last six penny sales tax
approval, the voters funded $6 million
to make improvements to our downtown. It
has made such a difference and I don't
want to lose the momentum that we made
over the past four years. Investing an
additional $4 million in our downtown
will continue to make it a destination
for tourism and a focal point for our
residents.
Our police department trains with their
weapons every month. The current shoot
house is falling apart and does not have
the capability to move walls to create
the different scenarios the trainers
would like to have. The police
department is asking for a million
dollars to build a new show house shoot
house with the flexibility to move the
walls and to improve their outdoor
firing line. This kind of training is
essential to prevent the unthinkable
events we see happening across the
country every year.
The largest request is to completely
remodel the municipal building we're
sitting in. It was completed in the late
1970s and the essential HVAC, electrical
and plumbing systems have started to
reach the end of their useful lives and
they now present operational safety and
reliability concerns I don't believe we
can further defer.
We've had to close this building what
two or three times now in the last few
years uh due to these kind of failures.
Additionally, the current current
configuration no longer supports the
needs of our operation. We used the $2.5
million approved by the voters on the
last six penny sales tax election to
start that plan for the remodel and $22
million is the request for this effort.
I believe we owe it to our employees to
give this building attention and moving
all the public-f facing municipal
services to the first floor will make a
big improvement in our customer service.
Johnson pool. Now, that's an amenity
that people have loved for many years,
but after 71 years, it's finally reached
the end of its life. We spent the
funding approved on the last six penny
sales tax selection for the design to
replace the pool. By choosing the
outdoor option, we'll save money on the
construction and the ongoing operation
costs. 10,400,000
is the cost to build this new Johnson
outdoor pool.
Unfortunately, many very worthy projects
did make my list uh of priorities. U and
I'd like to just go through those real
quickly. Fire station 6 replacement did
not make the cut. The fire department
prioritized station 2 due to the need to
serve the new growth areas, but we are
collecting public safety funds with
every new building constructed. I've
asked the staff to conserve these funds
so we can focus on building fire station
6 in the future and we currently have $2
million towards that effort.
Reed Avenue was approved in 2017 and we
spent the last 5 years trying to gain
railroad approval to do the project.
We've made great progress in gaining
their approval and I do believe we'll
eventually we'll be able to sign an
agreement with the Burlington Northern
Railroad. We've been told it will take
at least 18 months to get there. I
believe it would be irresponsible to put
funding for a project on the ballot
where we don't own the property and we
don't have permission to construct.
Engineer Cobb has shared with me that he
believes that we can build the Reed
Avenue project for much much less than
the $14 million estimated by the
consultants.
I propose that we save the remaining
funds left from the 2017 ballot, use it
as a match for a grant request to the
state, and maybe use a little bit of our
general fund reserves to construct the
project. We have gained those approvals.
Engineer Cobb is working on the
estimates, but we think we can build it
for maybe about a third or just slightly
over a third of what that engineer
estimate is.
The pump house is another project that
didn't make the list, but it's been on
our agenda a lot recently. After we
voted to remove the demolition deadline,
Director Sanchez came to me with an idea
to make the pump house the new
headquarters for the Clean and Safe
project.
We've been looking for a couple years,
Jason and I have in our downtown for a
warehouse and a place for the clean and
safe, but nothing has become available.
This is a project that I think we should
pay for with general fund reserves. We
have an estimate around $3 million and
we're working to get that finalized, but
we would solve two problems. We would
save the pump house and we'd find a home
for the clean and safe program.
Five years ago, I was concerned that we
might not be in a position to afford the
minimum revenue guarantees to
required uh to maintain our passenger
air service at the airport. Our budget
feature at that time was not
it was a concern.
The voters approved the MRG request and
at the end of November, we still had
1.25 million left in that account. I
feel that commercial passenger service
is a very high priority for the
community, but I didn't rank it high
enough to make the ballot is I believe
with the $1.25 million left, we'll be
able to use our budget, which I think is
growing, to be able to fund the MRG
until the end of the next six penny
sales tax.
Another project that um I fully support
is the old airport terminal. And I'm
really excited about that project.
Bringing a res restaurant, a museum, an
art center to the uh site at the old uh
terminal would be amazing. I just didn't
rank the $4 million project high enough
for it to make the ballot. But I do want
to work with the airport to find a way
to make this project happen.
But the police department asked for
$975,000
to purchase two multi-purpose rescue
vehicles to replace their current
military surplus vehicles. the new
vehicles would just fit better in an
urban law enforcement environment, but I
couldn't fit them onto the budget. But
now that we know exactly what they're
looking for, I believe that we'll be
able to find alternative ways to pay for
that in the future. And lastly, the
police department asked for $500,000 to
construct a multi-bay storage building
to hold all their various equipment, do
it in one place, and I support this
project and would recommend rather than
waiting for the sixth penny that we use
general fund reserves and make it happen
right away. Mr. President, those are my
recommendations for the next six penny.
I look forward to our discussions and I
really look forward to uh selling and
educating the public uh and the Larmy
County voters about these projects.
Thank you.
>> Thank you so much, Mr. Mayor. We
appreciate that. Um any questions uh
from the committee for the mayor before
we open it up to the public?
Any questions on his recommendations?
Okay. Uh let's open the the discussion
up to the public. Anyone in the room? Uh
would you like to discuss the proposed
items?
Okay, here we go.
Sir, if you could come up and just uh
push the button there and the green
light will come on and identify yourself
and
>> Good day uh Mr. Chairman, Mr. Mayor,
distinguished council members. Uh thank
you for the opportunity to speak. I
support uh the proposal from the mayor.
I think it's all a very good idea. My
only concern is and and no disrespect
for the people that use this building. I
live in an old building as well. Um it's
not cheap to maintain old buildings and
it's certainly a terrible idea to let it
go into disrepair and replace it. I
believe that the cost is about three
times what the mayor is asking for. So
that is clearly not not the way to go
letting the building fall into
disrepair. But um you see some of like
our police force and our first
responders, I think that they should
have the utmost priority uh in funding.
So my question would be what are those
things? And I haven't seen the budget. I
I I used to do maintenance engineering,
so I appreciate something about building
maintenance. What of those items for the
building must be done versus those items
for the building that would really be
nice and which of those items would be
uh would be able to improve buildings uh
customer service because I it is the the
city's building. It's the people's
building. So, I I I understand why $22
million is not an unreasonable number,
but given restraint in funding, um I
don't know if it's the exact time to
spend that kind of money on this
building. So, that's all I had to say
about that. Thank you for the
opportunity, sir.
>> Could you please identify yourself for
the record, please?
>> John Thomas. I live in a ward one.
>> Thank you, sir. Appreciate it. Thank you
for coming. Anyone else? Anyone else in
the room? Yes, sir.
Good evening, Council members and Mayor
Pat Collins. My name is Steve Millia
from Shy Wyoming here and I would I
think the proposal is very good all the
way through. I would like to say maybe
the fire station should take more
precedence over the municipal because if
a fire breaks out, uh when I drive down
Horse Peak Road, I can just imagine a a
prairie fire breaking out, wind coming
through and wiping out all kinds of
houses. Uh, and I think fire station
would be really, really good. And
maintaining this building, yes, if I had
to choose one or the other, I would
choose the fire station. Also, I like
the idea about the roads. Maybe a little
bit more money on the roads. I know
between uh Del Range and Story Pouse and
uh uh Yellowstone, those residential
roads are already pretty beat up. I live
in that particular area and I I walk it
a lot. And so maybe more money for
those. uh Warren and Central are utterly
fantastic that you get a uh super nice
job and uh Del Range fantastic. The
residential roads that uh that area I
had mentioned uh they are pretty well
beat up and I've heard a lot of people a
lot of my neighbors and other people
saying that it would really be nice if
we could get those roads repaved or or
something. Uh I know that uh one road up
there at Ditman uh by Hobs Elementary
School is still a dirt road which uh
it's been that way for obviously
forever. So uh priorities uh the fire
station and the road repair are
fantastic. Everything else it looks
really really good. So I appreciate your
time with that. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone else? Yes,
sir.
Uh Jim Ridgeway, 3615 Moore Avenue. Uh
Mr. President, Mayor Collins, uh just a
couple Colin comments. Um I do uh
probably agree with the majority of
Mayor Collins uh recommendations.
I do have a couple things. I think that
uh instead of putting the the turnout
equipment, the $1 million on the sixth
penny, that that could come from I think
city uh general fund reserves. I think
the city has a significant amount of
reserves that they could use for that.
Uh the other the other question I have
is on the 4 million for downtown
improvements. Um, if we go back to 2021,
I believe that um, the downtown hole was
mentioned as a I guess a a work item on
that money and we haven't seen any
movement on that. So, I'd kind of like
to know what the plan is for that.
>> Mr. Chairman,
>> Mr. Mayor, please.
>> I can't answer that question. Um the
downtown money was not part of uh the
whole but we did put a a large project
completion fund and we we we talked
about uh the whole as being one of
those. um maybe four or five months ago
now, we entered into an agreement with
leads to create a revolving loan fund
with those dollars and we have a partner
um that is working on a housing project
and some retail that uh hopefully we'll
see happen sometime in this next year.
Um,
I'm trying to think of the the name of
the Overland Group is the uh developer
that's looking at the uh uh at doing
that project in partnership with the
Full Circle Realy that owns the
building. And uh the $3 million that we
have uh has been put into that revolving
loan fund. And the idea would be is that
over the next number of years, those
dollars will come back to us and that we
use those dollars again to find another
project in the downtown that needs those
dollars. And so, um you're right, sir.
It's been tough to find a partner on
this one, but we have one now and we're
hoping that we're moving forward.
>> Okay. And then, Mr. President, uh, also
any of that $4 million, is that going to
be used for any type of um
I guess the the work on the 15th Street
train that that's going down there or is
that just going to be, you know, core
sidewalks, things of that nature?
>> That's our int that's our intent at this
point, sir. It's a curb gutter sidewalk.
U the last last project we've done a lot
of work at the at the depot and the
plaza the 17 street lights those types
of things are what we're looking at
maintaining
um that's what we're trying to do with
the with the new funds.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um the other question
and comment is back in 2021 on the the
road maintenance there was a a project
for the Missile Drive Crow Creek bridge
and I I haven't seen any movement on
that is if anybody could advise any kind
of status on when that project would go
and is do we have the money still or are
we going to have to draw from this four
million?
>> Director Cobb, thank you for being here.
your
>> welcome.
>> Um, President Crave, um, to through you
to to you, sir. Um, the answer is right
now it's in design. Um, we have a
consultant on board that's been working
on the design of the bridge and the
reconfiguration of the intersection. Um,
we don't have it fully funded yet. Um,
but we're looking at several
opportunities to do that in in the near
future,
>> but that would not include or Mr.
President, through you, that would not
include this current 4 million. We're
going to use the 2021
monies for that. Correct. Mr. Mr.
>> President Cra. Yes. What what we can,
sir. Yes.
>> Okay. Um the other one is is a comment
on uh the Reed Corridor uh did not make
the the cut off. I was just going to
make a a comment on that.
um by the I think the city's example, it
was a it's a rail industrial corridor
and one of the um artist renditions that
I saw showed a lot of greenway. There
was grass, there was trees, benches,
things of that nature. The the question
I have is and it you may not be able to
do it, but has the city done any soil
testing of that area? Because when we
talk about railroad and industrial, we
talk about contaminated soil.
>> Yes, sir.
>> And we also talk about remediating that
soil which is expensive.
>> Yes, sir. Director Cobb, can you help us
with that, please?
>> President C. Gra. Yes. Through you, sir.
To Mr. Rididgeway, I got to clarify
something on my last response to make
sure that I understand. So, when you
said the 2021, what we're using is fifth
penny money for for the for that project
for 19th and missile. Fifth penny
overage account and some money. Okay.
somebody that's been dedicated to the
project.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> And and sir through through you again.
Um to answer your question about the
soil testing, it is part of our next
phase. We have a design element in we
got have a grant from the FRA which our
match is roughly $150,000.
But in that we have $95,000 to do an
environmental assessment and that
consultant will get get started here um
end of February, first part of March.
>> Okay. Um thank you for that. And just a
comment on that is I don't know um what
the the soil is going to show, but I
don't know if it's the city's
responsibility or if the city could work
with the railroad is if there is
significant contamination to clean that
up. And I also agree with with Mayor
Collins. I think that the city should
probably wait until we have more than a
30%
uh commitment from the railroad before
we pump in tax dollar money.
>> Thank you, Mr. Rididgeway. Appreciate
your comments. Anyone else?
>> Yes, sir. Welcome.
>> Thank you, President Crave. Mr. Mayor,
Jim Walter. I live at uh 4019 Faring
Farthing Road over in Ward 3. Uh I also
uh currently serve as the chairman of
the Greenway Advisory Council and just
would like to thank the mayor and thank
the council for putting the two greenway
projects on here. Um the greenway is one
of those projects that when it's on the
ballot, it touches every neighborhood of
the city. You know, downtown is, you
know, touches Ward One and um the but
the greenway, it's in W one, it's in W
two, it's in W three. I used to live
over on in ward one over on the south
side. It was one of the greatest
amenities we had on the south side is
the amount of greenway and there are
members on this council. Councilman
Lelaybornne of course has been banging
the drum for the greenway for a lot of
years but a lot of support and we
appreciate that. Uh the maintenance
piece of it at $3 million is incredibly
important because as we mentioned we've
got nearly 50 miles and and some of it's
aging and some of it needs to be
addressed. But at the same time, I want
to thank uh Director Sanchez and his
crew uh for the amazing work that they
do. And that maintenance dollars allows
us to have the maintenance crews out on
the greenway. They're mowing it. They're
abading graffiti when it's out there.
They're sealing cracks to make sure that
it's safe and we're not having tripping
injuries. And uh best of all, um they
plow the snow quicker than the city road
department does. So uh we really
appreciate that and uh we appreciate
your consideration in including it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Anyone else in the room
uh before I go online? Anyone else like
to make a comment?
Okay, Jennifer, do we have any any uh
online comments?
Okay, no online comments. All right, we
will close the uh public comment for
this part of the meeting and I'll bring
it back up on the dis. If we could get a
motion in a second, we will talk about
it. I would move to approve.
>> Moved by Dr. Aldridge, second by
Councilman White. Discussion from the
committee.
>> I Oh. Uh, Mr. Chairman, uh, through you.
Uh, I would like to, uh, move by a
substitute. I'll explain if I can have a
second for discussion.
>> We have a request for substitute. Is
there a second for it?
>> I would second for discuss sake of
discussion.
>> Second by Dr. Aldridge.
>> Okay.
>> Councilman Moody. Thank you, Mr.
President. Through you. So, for
everybody in the public, um if you look
at page two, number three, my proposal
instead of $9 million for roads, $20
million. And I'll explain why. Cuz uh
Mr. Cobber, city engineer, gave a great
presentation October, uh saying how we
need probably at least $20 million in
order to have the roads in really good
shape over the years. So, that's what
I'm looking at. Plus, based on the
surveys that uh Mr. Murphy sent out to
us on December 18th, and I actually uh
calculated the likely somewhat likely,
the roads have a 75% potential support.
That's super super majority. Plus, from
our 2021 six penny, it was asked for 14
uh million and it passed 71%.
So, that's my we're doing it. Plus, this
has the most support within the city.
And then if you look at number uh 10,
I took out the municipal remodel
project. I think there's other ways we
can look at the money potentially from
our reserves or through a bond like the
spiker garage.
Fire station number six. It was
mentioned, I know I've had constituents
and also based on the survey, we've seen
what's happened with the recent fires.
We need to have the most up-to-date,
best professional equipment for our
firefighters and fire station number six
does need replacement relocation
project. I'm aware that was $9 million.
The reason it's 11 million again to be
consistent with funding plus there could
be inflationary cost. So that's why I
said $1 million. Everything else, ladies
and gentlemen, is the same. Okay,
everything else is the same. That is the
only two changes I have in the
substitute and I look forward to hear
what the public says and also from my
colleagues.
>> Let me um just recap if I can.
>> So you you your uh motion is to um
increase this uh number three the city
street maintenance project from 9
million to 20 million. Sir,
>> so you'd add $11 million there and
number 10, you would remove $22 million
uh in total and then you propose adding
station number six for $11 million.
>> Sir,
>> and that would balance out to the total
dollars.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Let's open it up to discussion. Um we
have a motion and a second. We better go
to the public and get some comments.
Anyone like to comment on this uh
proposed uh substitute
discussion from the committee?
>> Mr. President.
>> Yes, Dr. R.
>> I just wanted to point out to my
colleague from W three that the Spiker
garage was paid for through revenue
bonds. We cannot do revenue bonds for
this building. It would still have to be
if we're going to bond to do this
building, we would still have to go out
for an election and use our bonding
capacity.
>> Further discussion,
>> Mr. Chairman,
>> Mr. Chairman, through you. Well, first
and foremost, I want to make sure that
everyone understands that when uh
Councilman Moody was saying that road
maintenance uh had a 75%
um
support from the community. I'm assuming
that that is adding the likely and
somewhat likely numbers together,
which I think is really important
because I think it's misleading to let
people think that that's 75% likely.
Mr. President,
>> uh, thank you, Mr. President. Uh, yes, I
did have that and I even have this
document, too. I've emailed some
constituents this, but yes, 50% 56%
likely, somewhat likely. It said 75%
potential support. So it is documented
here. So I do apologize for misspeaking.
>> Uh
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> Chairman Crave, I also um I'm really
concerned quite honestly. We have a
responsibility I believe as a city
council for roughly 550 employees. Um
many are spread out throughout the
community. They don't work necessarily
in this building. Um but we know that um
this building has had some issues that
have caused us to have to relocate stu
uh students. Oh my gosh, it's been a
long day. Relocate employees uh twice
over the last five years um for
different varying amounts of time.
So, I think that while um perhaps the
ask um of 22 million, I believe is what
was in the mayor's ask um could probably
we might be able to do that
peace meal. Although the plan we saw
basically took down the building around
the elevator. I mean, a lot of that was
moving the elevators and different
things. So, I don't know how peace meal
we could do that. But I'm also uh so I'm
concerned about employees and working in
this building. Although I I want to
definitely recognize that we have a
fleet maintenance building that is way
beyond need of repair. Um that is, you
know, questionable for the safety of the
people working there and the and the
activities taking place there and needs
to be replaced or significantly
remodeled. But I'm also concerned about
our um constituents on the Reed Avenue
corridor. While that's not in the ward
that I represent, at the end of the day,
I think we all agree that we represent
the entire community. And um we have um
been presented with um a plan by our
city engineer that has um
uh a full sl a full menu, if you will,
of options for the Reed Avenue corridor
and also a what I would call a
restrained budget amount that was
presented to us. Um, and I don't see
anywhere in either one of these um
documents where we've we've
done anything with Reed Avenue corridor,
which I really believe is a commitment
we need to look at that we may have made
to the people in on the Reed Avenue
corridor um with the uh sales tax um
election that was done two two election
two elections ago that we have not held
up our end of the bargain there. So, um
I have concerns on both of the amendment
and on the original um legislation
espe
>> thank you Mr. President through you. Uh
when I first read the sub uh I really
liked it. Uh then I got to thinking
about the conversation we had Monday
night about the health, welfare, and
safety of the citizens. And
uh it brought me back to the people that
are closest to us, the lifeblood of this
city, the backbone of this city, and
actually the brains of this city, our
people over there. Um if we can't show
them the commitment of looking out for
their health, welfare, and safety,
um
I think it it gets kind of hypocritical
of us in a way. Um we should be taking
care of our employees. Uh I know we have
done that with uh colas and trying to
keep up with uh raises. Uh I know we're
going to have more of that discussion
during the budget again and it and we
need to
um but
yeah this building I mean I grew up in
this neighborhood and uh I think it was
built when I was
eight nine years old.
>> 78.
>> Yeah. So, it it it definitely needs some
major attention. Um, and uh talking to
our employees
uh of what they've went through. You
know, uh us on the council, we're in
here hours. They're in here uh days,
weeks, months, and uh it's like I said,
we we do owe them that consideration. I
know it's when you put something out
there on a ballot like this, you're
you're going to have to educate the the
public about why all these projects are
needed.
Um, so I guess if I I was a a vet man
and I wanted to uh get out there and
educate the people, it would be for the
the $22 million for this building.
>> Thank you, Councilman. Uh, Councilman
White. Uh, thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Through you, um, really appreciate the
mayor's proposals. Um, I I echo my
colleague from W three, uh, Dr. Aldridge
uh, concerns about Reed Avenue being um,
left off. Um
I I do think that
a large part of the reason why we've
seen such an increase in capital
investment along Reed Avenue corridor,
many new businesses,
um new buildings,
um is because that they were of the
opinion that the city would follow
through with that. And um while I know
that the the mayor's proposal included
reasoning on on why um he left it off
and an an alternative plan uh once the
approval from the railroad uh was
obtained. Um
I I just really hope we can find a way
to include it somehow.
Uh also
uh to my uh colleague other colleague
from W 3 Mr. Moody with your uh
proposal.
I I see no way we can leave off the uh
the city building project.
It's this building is 47
48 years old.
um the the the times that we have had to
relocate employees due to health
concerns,
um HVAC concerns, heating concerns,
um those problems are only going to get
worse if we delay this any further. And
u
you know, Mr. Esabel made a great
statement. If we're not going to take
care of our employees,
the ones that that do the work every
single day, um you know, then
then what are we doing? Um the one thing
uh in the comments that have been made
thus far uh that no one's mentioned
about the municipal building remodel
project, you know, this building was
built pre-ADA
and so having a major remodel like the
one um included
in the mayor's recommendations includes
complete ADA accessibility upgrades. And
if you have been in the halls uh of the
various floors or even the restrooms,
you know that that is severely needed.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman White. Uh I'm
going to open it up to more comments,
but let's keep it keep it focused on the
uh proposed substitute. Uh
Dr. Emmens, go ahead.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. So, um I wanted to
talk about the building also.
I think that and I'm coming at this from
a little bit different standpoint. Um I
absolutely think it's important for the
health and safety of our of our
employees. But I think we also need to
keep in mind that this is the
community's building. This is not just
our building. This serves every
individual in this city. Um and as
stewards of the city's finances and
resources, we are responsible for that.
Um if we're not going to be taking care
of it, who who will do that? I mean,
that that in in my opinion is our
responsibility.
And if we don't do it, we're being
irresponsible and we're not being good
stewards.
Um, as somebody who, um, works every day
in a building owned by the county, I
make sure that that building doesn't get
to the point where it slides so much I
can't afford to fix it or the county
can't afford to fix it. And I think
that's the problem. It's not like we've
put money into the building every year.
That that wouldn't that would have been
a great idea to have been doing that all
along. And I'm hoping that going forward
we can so that we've got an annual
maintenance program, but if we wait,
it's just going to keep costing us more.
It's not ever going to be any cheaper.
Um, and I I think considering the fact
that the um voters during the last six
penny vote gave us um authority
$2 million, $2.5 million to do a plan
for the building was them recognizing
that this is their building and that
they want us to take care of it. And
when you look at how that scored last
year or last time, and I know there are
different proposals in each category out
of 14 propositions, that was number six.
>> Point of order. We're this the building
is not on the amendment.
>> Yes, it is.
>> He's removing.
>> If he took it off, it is.
>> Okay. So, okay. Thank you.
>> It's it's good.
So, um I I'm going to speak against I am
speaking against the amendment um for
that reason. Um so that's what I wanted
to say.
>> Thank you uh Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Um I'd like to
thank the public uh for their comments.
Um Mr. Moody for uh sparking this
conversation, speaking on and against
the substitute. Um, we need a municipal
building. The mayor's proposal is to
begin working on that right now, using
our reserves to pay for that
construction as it gets underway and
repay ourselves from the hopefully
approved six penny. And I applaud that
suggestion. I think that is uh needed.
We've got design work underway and um it
um this is I think an absolutely
essential element in the six penny
ballot and we need all need to commit to
working to get it passed and I thank uh
mayor and the amber for putting it in
there. When I first got appointed, the
first thing I did was to start spending
time on the six penny, went through
three or four variations of a of a
comprehensive spreadsheet on it. Um, and
then we got the mayor's letter and his
recommendations
aligned uh almost exactly with the kind
of thinking I had, which also included
an analysis of the Reed Avenue project.
I hold my remarks on that until we
actually talk about resolution of the
mayors. Um and um roads
uh Mr. Cobb u does an incredible job
with road management. Um the mayor's $9
million uh and his proposal to uh use
overreach funds uh will certainly help
uh and um and there may be other
opportunities. Um but one thing Mr. Cobb
will also tell you is um there are
limitations in how much we can actually
spend because we can't get contractors
to do the work. Um so I think the mayor
and uh his staff and Mr. Cobb have tried
to find the appropriate balance and uh
that's why I think we should leave it at
$9 million and um that's why I'm going
to vote no on the substitute.
>> Thank you. Councilman Councilman Moody.
Uh thank you uh Mr. President. Thank you
everyone for your comments. Uh I am
willing to compromise on this. So I'd
like to amend my substitute. So for
number 10, we'll put back in the
proposal that is already there, the
municipal building remal project and
that will be 11 uh million for then the
building. So I understand everywhere
everybody's perspective is and I'm
willing to compromise on that. So, we'll
keep 20 million with the roads, but 11
million for the building. Just a
compromise. And I would entertain a
second at least for discussion and also
for the public to comment.
>> So, we have a motion to amend the
substitute.
Uh, is there a second?
>> Thank you. Second by Councilman Esel.
Discussion or I guess we should go to
the public. Anybody want to Mr.
Rididgeway?
Uh, Chairman Crave, uh, just a question
that I was going to make a comment on
the fire station six. Is that still in
this block or not?
>> No,
>> we're going to come back to it, though.
>> Um, Mr. Chairman, let me do one more.
>> Yes, sir.
>> President Crave, Steve Millia, I think
the compromise is is good. Uh, the
building does need to be worked on.
roads need. So I uh go along with the uh
proposal.
>> Yeah. And Mayor Collins,
>> Mr. President, threw you to the
committee. One of the things we talked
about when we started the six penny
sales tax project was to try not to
partially fund projects because what
staff has shared with us is um we give
them $11 million, but our expectation is
that they're going to do the whole thing
and there's no funding to do that. So,
you know, giving it half of the money
doesn't doesn't meet that. And and what
can we do? We can't do the things that
really need to be done. Um or at least
enough of it. And and so I think what
puts us in just in a really bad tough
spot, especially for staff who's trying
to navigate how do you do that and not
not deliver the final product. Um and
then I would just share with you again a
little bit of what Mr. Wolf said. Um and
I just went over to talk to our engineer
just to make sure. We probably would
have put more money on for roads if
there was capacity for contractors to do
it. But what we've learned is they're
saturated. There's so much work to do
and there's less crews to do it that we
can't do more than about $10 million a
year. And so the request that we've made
is in recognition of that. Um it's funny
because when we first started 5 years
ago, we didn't have enough money and we
and there were contractors, but today
that's flipped. There's not as many
crews to do the work and um and money is
not as big a challenge to us. Um, so I
would ask that uh if you're going to
fund the building, we fund it completely
um so we can bring success.
>> Thank you. Anyone else in the public
that would like to speak on the proposed
amendment to the substitute?
Miss Nimichek,
Vicky Nimichek, public works. I would
just like to add a few things just to uh
what the uh council has discussed about
the building municipal building
renovation. Um the electrical, the HVAC,
and the plumbing are all well beyond
their life expectancy.
There's been no upgrade to those systems
at all. I don't know if anybody can feel
it, but it's about 77 in here right now.
Last night it was warmer than that. Um,
I had them work on adjusting that today,
but this building was designed with an
open floor plan and we have totally
disbanded that open floor plan and our
HVAC system now just doesn't work
anymore. Our plumbing system, same
thing. You've got bathrooms that are not
only beyond the the plumbing is so
outdated, it's ridiculous, but you we
can't even clean the floors anymore.
there. There's no surface on those to
that can be cleaned. We've painted we've
done the best we can. We've put new
carpet in. We've It's that lipstick on a
pig. We've got a pig and we've been
putting lipstick on it for five decades
and we're 20 We're two decades past a
major renovation. Um, the ADA upgrades,
we're a we're doing a disservice to our
public by having the ADA
systems in this building are just are
atrocious. They are not up to par with
and they need to be fixed. Um, the
restrooms we uh we absolutely need to
gut those and and start again. Um, I
will say one additional thing is well
two additional things. First, the
elevators. The elevators are uh not
capable of even um having a a gurnie if
someone's sick or hurt or you can't lay
a gurnie down flat in those elevators.
The new plan has a new elevator design
that will meet those standards. Um and
then last is security. We live in an
entirely different world than we did
five decades ago. and we need to secure
not only the public but the employees as
well. Um the security the plan in this
uh that we're working on will have
people serving the public from windows
with bullet resistant glass uh type
things. Um we will have all of the
people that uh serve the public everyday
types of things will be on the first
floor. We'll have meeting rooms on the
first floor that people will be able to
go to so that we don't have to have
people walking throughout the building
when someone comes and needs something
from us. We can go downstairs meet on
the first floor and have a secure place
that doesn't expose the entire employee
the employee base and the entire
building to a security problem. So um we
have had security problems in the past.
We've tried to address those as best we
can, but the fact is is that those
security issues need to be addressed
before something significant happens and
it's just a matter of time in my
opinion. So, I did want to bring those
extra things up and I thank you for your
time.
>> Thank you. Anyone else in the public?
Uh, seeing none, we'll we'll bring it
back up to the uh dis for discussion on
the proposed amendment to the
substitute. Uh Dr. Renick,
>> thank you. President Crave, speaking
against the amendment, I have been
attending for the last couple months the
um meetings with the architect and the
staff
in going through the um plans for the
building. And at my request, I think we
have a work session scheduled here in
the very near future
um to hear from them. they're supposed
to have pretty much final drawings done
within a week and we'll have actually
more accurate
um dollar amounts within that time. But
in some of our discussions, the
discussion was, you know, can we
peacemeal this or can we phase this? And
according to the consultants, yes, we
can phase it. However, it would take
much longer and be much more expensive
to go in and just redo it and get it
done is the most coste effective way to
to do it. So I although I appreciate my
colleagues attempt to compromise um I
cannot support half a loaf.
>> Thank you. Further Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um President Crave through you. Um I
also am speaking against the amendment.
While I um appreciate the willingness to
compromise um it really isn't a
compromise if um we can't do the
project. And um my belief is is that
quite honestly I don't think 22 million
is going to be enough. I think that that
is far under um what is actually going
to cost even if we are do borrow the
money from ourselves. Um, as a reminder
to the public, we do have to also
replace um, my understanding is the
interest that's lost from that from us
using that money that could have been
made by the city um, on interest for
that money that we've borrowed. So, I
just um I I can't support the amendment.
Um,
while we may save a few dollars here and
there, quite honestly, I don't think
we've done our told our story very well.
um because of HIPPA regulations and
because of uh some of the other federal
requirements that we have to follow, I
don't know that this the community
understands that we have had employees
physically made physically ill by what
they believe is this building and that
um they aren't able to come to work and
know that they're going to be safe while
they're working in this building um for
a variety of reasons. So, I think that
we need to do a better job and
especially if uh this does end up on the
22 million does end up on the ballot, we
need to make sure that we do a good job
of explaining to the community how
urgent this is and how um important it
is. It doesn't matter if we can give
employees colas if they're dead. So, we
need to be able to make sure that they
last long enough that they can enjoy the
colas.
>> Wow. Okay. Thank you, Councilman Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Through you,
um, on the roads part of it, uh, maybe I
have a question for engineer Cobb.
How much more money could we put out
there every year with the construction
crews and what they can get done within
the the seasonal
aspects that they have to deal with?
What what's the most amount of money
that we could probably have then?
>> President Crave through you to um
>> you're adding a fifth penny on top.
>> So this is a complicated answer. Okay.
So, I can tell you the largest one I've
ever done, my total my total
construction budget was 28 million. What
happened was we ended up having to carry
over those projects into the next year,
which then had me shrink the next year's
budget. So, while I was able to put it
out, we had great bids for it. Those all
those projects carried over to the
following year because our we don't have
enough crews to do the work. So, my
sweet spot is a total of about 20
million. That includes both what I do
for capital slash what I call capital
construction, which is a lot of
maintenance as well, plus the standard
maintenance that I have. We don't always
have the funds to do it, but we did have
the reserves to do it. I've been
averaging 20 to 23 million a year total.
>> Okay,
>> that's really the sweet spot, but again,
that's that's that's the best I can
offer you. I can tell you that many
factors come into play with that. So,
for instance, if wide dots letings are
bigger, so then my I have to break that
down again. If if other projects are
going on as as some of these facilities
are being built, like for instance with
the meta facility, they're taking a lot
of those workers from the contractors
and they're working there now for them.
They're still contractors, but they're
out of state contractors that are hiring
in people that are local to do some of
the work. It's it's a really tough
answer. I wish I had a better one for
you, but my I I'll stay with I'm going
to say I think that 20 to 22 million
range total is about as far as I can go.
>> No, Mr. President, that that makes my
point by pouring more money in the
bucket really doesn't do us much good if
they can't spend it.
>> So, um that
would be against the amendment.
Um it remain to talk about the tax
situation.
>> No, not yet. Okay.
>> Anyone else?
>> I'll wait.
>> Anyone else want to speak on the
amendment to the substitute?
Um, Director Cobb, you want to say
something before we vote?
>> Yes, sir. Please, if I can. So, the
mayor and M. Ash pointed out to me. I
need to make sure that I clarify to you
that again this was this is fifth penny
and six penny combined. So, you you and
make sure that you understood that. Um,
so the ask that I originally had which
was set at the at I believe the 12
million mark. That's where I felt like
my maximum was. I the ask that I asked
you was where I thought my maximum would
be for that for the maintenance portion
of this for the six penny. I hope that
you understand that. Yes, sir. Thank
you. Thank you for the clarification.
Any further discussion on the amendment?
Hearing none. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> All right. The amendment to the
substitute fails. We're back on the
substitute. Further discussion on the
substitute. Dis
uh Dr. Renie.
>> No, Matt.
>> Okay. Further discussion hearing? None.
We're on the original substitute. All
those in favor signify by saying I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> The substitute fails. We're back to the
proposed resolution as presented by the
mayor.
>> Mr. President.
>> Uh Dr. Ring.
>> Um Mr. President,
the six penny tax is also known as the
specialurpose option tax
and it was designed
created specifically for projects that
we don't have the money to do in our
normal
um operations.
And we've done some great things. We
between us and the county, we've done
some great things with it. Some of the
things we've done are like we have built
three fire stations. We built a botanic
gardens. We've done the greenway all
these years. Um we did the public safety
center. So those are just some of the
projects we've done. The countyy's done,
you know, our award-winning library, the
jail archer complex.
Um but that's what it was designed for
was projects like that. And I have
watched with alarm as um every as
recurring costs which I think should
come out of the our budget have been
creeping into the sixth penny. I don't
think that's why it's created and I
think we're setting ourselves up for a
fall by putting recurring costs into the
into the tax um in the event that that a
portion of it
um or fails which at times has happened
in the past. So in view of that I would
like to make some amendments Mr.
president. And my first amendment is I
would like to delete the $9 million for
streets.
And if I can have a second, I'd like to
discuss it.
>> We have a motion and a second. Uh go
ahead and explain, please, Dr. Renie.
>> All right. So, Mr. President and and
colleagues, um part of what again this
is a recurring cost. Um, when I
protested, the first time we put street
funds in there, I think was during the
or administration. I protested that a
little bit. I protest a little when we
did the 14 million or whatever it was
last time and was told, "No, this isn't
going to be a recurring expense. Um,
and obviously it's become a recurring
expense, Mr. Mr. President." And I've
done a little bit of research and
according to what I've been able to find
out, there is still
$2.25 million unencumbered dollars left
over from the 2015 to 2018 tax. There is
17.5 million unencumbered dollars left
over from
um 2019 to 2022.
And there is still $31.3 million left
over from the most recent
um fifth penny tax. We received actually
for street and alley 30 million in the
last fifth penny tax and I think we can
probably expect to receive another 30
million in the next fifth penny tax. And
that gives street almost 80 over $80
million in funds.
So, and we've just been told that the
maximum they could ever spend
is maybe $23 million. And and the mayor,
I think, proved my point that we've been
spending 10 million here, I think the
figure was that he gave us. So, looking
at the fact, and perhaps, you know, Mr.
Cobb can explain to me why I'm
incorrect, but looking at the figures,
we have about we will have currently
have 51 million and should gain another
30 million in funds for street and
alley. I think that's enough. Therefore,
I'd like to remove the $9 million.
We have a motion and a second to remove
item number three, which is a city
street maintenance project for $9
million. Uh let's open it up to the
public for discussion on this item.
>> Mr. Chairman, before you maybe I could
answer a little bit of that.
>> Yep.
>> I asked these exact same questions to
staff when um when we were preparing for
putting the ballot together.
All of the money that uh Dr. Ernie
talked about the 2015 money. Um we have
a project that's in design right now
that those dollars are allocated to. The
same thing for the last six penny sales
tax. We have what uh we call the TIP,
the transportation improvement plan. And
uh that plan right now for years 26, 27,
28, 29, and 30 um has about $169 million
worth of projects that are that are that
are slated for that. Um
and so
what we're talking about with the $9
million is is actual maintenance money.
But some of these other projects are
like the Missile Drive project that uh
um Mr. Ridgeway spoke about earlier and
a bunch of other projects that Mr. Cobb
can talk about, but these are projects
like 18th Street. We're going to
remodel, redo 18th Street, improve the
drainage to protect downtown. Very
expensive project. Uh that's going to be
done over the next four or five years.
And so, um,
I appreciate that it looks tough when
you when you look at those dollars and
see there's $2 million left from 2015,
but there's a long-term project that
they've been planning to do. Mr. Cob
will have to remind me what that project
is. But, um, you know, if we if we get
rid of all those dollars, then there's
no money to do the the major
construction parts of those, the capital
projects. Um, and so I think that puts
us in into a challenge. And I do I do
respect the the concept. When, uh, the
six penny sales tax was first built, um,
it only allowed for construction of new
roads. It didn't allow for, uh, the
maintenance of roads. And if I remember
right, it was you and I, um, that were
on the city council at the time. Uh, so
this has been a while ago. U, Jim Bert
was a representative here. And, um, we
were getting after him about, uh, you
know, do something for us. He goes,
"Well, what do you want?" And we said,
"Well, the six penny sales tax, we can
build these beautiful roads, but we
never have enough money to maintain
them." And uh so if you're going to do
something that would really help us,
change the state law to allow us to be
able to do maintenance on our roads
because it doesn't make any sense to
build them and let them deteriorate to
the point where we can't continue to to
service them. And by God, he got to the
legislature as a Democrat and he got
enough people to do it and it became the
law. And so that tells you the support
that there was in the legislature. And
so I I would call upon Mr. Cobb maybe to
talk about the tip so that as the people
are coming forward to make their
comments he'd understand why those
numbers are still there.
>> Director Cobb
>> President Crave through you to Dr.
Renie. So Dr. Renie first of all the
first project that you spoke of what was
the total amount sir
microphone
>> through you Mr. President to director
Cobb. I referred to the 2015 to 2018
ballot. There's 2.25 million still
unencumbered as of this these figures
are as of December 13th.
>> Director Cob President Crave threw you
to Dr. Renie. Dr. Renie, that project is
for the Yellowstone Dell range project
is currently trying to be designed. Um,
and it's been on the books for that long
because we just haven't been able to do
it. but it's for the signal replacement
and operational improvements of the
corner of Dell Range and Yellowstone. As
you all know, in the afternoons, there's
quite a backup through there and that
pavement is failing. Um, when you look
when you're going westbound, um, there's
a lot of ruting. Um, it's a maintenance
project. It's a largecale maintenance
project, but it's it's it's going to
take all of that money and even more.
Right now, I currently have slated
approximately
3.5 million, sir.
It's just not showing as encumbered, but
it's we're working on it now.
And to answer your question related to
the six penny money that's remaining,
um, while you don't feel like it's
encumbered, it's not encumbered, but it
is programmed. It's programmed this
summer for what I call Dell Range phase
2, which is from Powderhouse to Sunset.
The project that I was just speaking
about before goes from Sunset forward.
So that those two projects are basically
right next to each other.
>> Further questions for Director C.
>> No, sorry. No, Mr. President, I'll save
my comments for our discussion.
>> Okay, further uh discussion from the
public.
Anyone want to comment on this proposed
substitute? All right, public comment is
closed. Um let's bring it back up for
discussion.
>> Mr. President,
>> Dr. really
>> I'm I'm not saying the projects I mean I
realize we pro we have programmed out
there years worth of projects.
What I'm saying is I think that in the
view of the fact that we can't do rarely
do we do $20 million worth of projects
um in a year. We have the funding that's
required for most of those projects. I
don't think we're going to find the
contracts or turn them out quick enough
to spend the $81 million that we have or
will have.
>> Um, Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Um, I just have a
clarifi clarifying question
um for the engineer. So, the $80 million
that we have out there, when do you uh
anticipate all those projects would be
completed by?
Best guess.
So, President Crave through you to Dr.
Emmens. So, Dr. sermons as I some of the
as I've this is this is this is it's not
as easy to just explain this as easy as
I want to but what I'm going to tell you
is as I said to you before we talked
about I've got to give some context so
we talked about the amount of work that
we can put out per year right well some
of these are specialty projects that
we're going to attract contractors
outside some some of these large scale
bridge replacement projects I've got
fifth and deming coming we've got the
bridge replacement at 19th and missile
we are going to attract some contractors
outside that will look at this work
because they're big enough for them to
do. So, it's it's like when Christensen
was built, although Ryman had a primary
component to that, which was a local
contractor, they brought in
subcontractors from other areas that
were able to help us from from northern
part of the state. There was some from
Colorado that came in. So, this helps
our market, right? So, these these
questions that you say, every time I go
into this, it leads to more questions.
But I'm I'm I hope as what I've got
programmed here for the next five years,
um at least from the what I think would
be a normal budget, I'm looking at it
right now on my screen. See,
let me see if I can add it sideways
here.
30 40 50 60 70. So I think within the
next five years or four and a half is
what I based on my programming if we're
able to do everything we want to do I
will have it spent.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> Dr. one further question. So and I'm not
um questioning your work load. I know
you you guys work super hard and and get
a lot done, but I I just want to make
sure that with these projects that
you're talking about now and with the
anticipated maintenance that we're
looking at with this $9 million, is that
something that can even be accomplished
within the time period that the six
penny would cover, or is that something
that we need to look that may be
spreading out over more time. And I get
that that goes right back to my earlier
argument that the longer we wait, the
more expensive things become. But I'd
like your input on that.
>> Director C.
>> President Crave threw you to um Dr.
Emmens. So Dr. Emmens, I truly believe
or I wouldn't have asked for it. I think
the original 12 million that I talked
about before was realistic between what
we have in the bank and what I need to
do for maintenance and what I have
available. I believe that we can spend
that in the the time frame that I'm
looking at, which is within that 4-year
period that we collect. Now, again, that
collection starts, but it takes just
like what we did with the six penny
previously for road maintenance. I
wasn't able to spend anything out of
that account until year two because it
takes a while to start collecting funds.
There's a misconception that I
instantaneously can start spending the
money the minute the voters say yes
because we haven't even collected it
yet. So it takes time for that that
money to roll in. So I it's it's a
4-year period with after that which is
why we have the lag that Dr. Renie
pointed out the collection I couldn't
spend anything in the first year. So
that is always kind of a dead year for
me with the with whoever we choose. Now
could have we taken some out of overage
and used it then? Yes. But I I I chose
to kind of spread it out over time and
took we did use some of the overage
money to be able to to looking at some
of the maintenance projects that we
already had on the books. I hope that
answers your question, ma'am. I may have
confused you more.
>> Thank you, director. Um Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh President Crave through you. I would
I just want to
uh put this in context is that my
understanding is we have and please
correct me if I'm wrong, mayor or
engineer Cobb, uh about 350 miles of
street surface that we maintain here in
the city.
>> Okay.
>> 370
>> 370 and that right now we are paying
about a million dollars a mile for road
construction.
President Crave through you to to Dr.
Aldridge. Yes, that's what Doug's been
getting it. We've been getting about a
million dollars from maintenance right
now. So,
>> yeah. So, I mean, when we talk about $9
million, we're really talking about nine
miles of road. Um, and many of these
large projects,
while I know that we, you know, having
money and savings sometimes is frowned
upon because we really want to get it
out on these projects, um, it does take
time to collect it and the money we
collected back in 2015 2018 uh, doesn't
go nearly as far today as what it did in
2015 to 2018. Um, and statutoily road
taking care of roads is one of our
primary responsibilities as a council,
our city roads, and it's also one of the
things that I hear from constituents all
the time is about taking care of our
infrastructure and maintaining our city
streets. Um, I won't go into detail in
pointing out that all of these major
projects that have been noted, uh, very
few of them are in W three, but I
understand that sometimes it doesn't
work out evenly. Um, so I just would
like to, um, say that for that reason, I
will not be able to support this
amendment.
>> Further discussion on the substitute.
Dr. R.
>> Mr. President, just to make my my final
point, um we're talking the monies I'm
talking about are fifth penny monies. So
that's over the last three um fifth
pennies. We have we still have $51
million sitting there that's programmed
but not encumbered. We anticipate
another 30 million at least in the next
fifth penny. Plus, we had 14 million in
the last six penny and I think three
million in the sixth penny before that.
So, that's almost $und00 million that
that that this that street alley has
been funded for. Um I don't think they
can spend it that quickly.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldridge.
>> One more comment. President Crave, I
think that um that may be a precocious
assumption that we can count on the
fifth penny sales tax generating $30
million. Uh that's assuming we are given
that opportunity by our voters.
>> Mr. Chairman, if I could just add one
thing,
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> we have a challenge, I think, with our
roads. When we took office um 5 years
ago, many of you were uh part of that,
we estimated that we had $150 million
worth of deferred maintenance on our
roads, meaning that we needed to spend
$150 million in 20 January of 2021 to
stabilize our roads. And we recognized
that, you know, both with the capacity
of our contractors and just the
availability of the money, we didn't
have it. And so we were trying to make a
commitment five years ago that we would
we would fund roads um at a level that
would allow us to start to catch up to
that. I know inflation makes that
difficult, but um and and then the fact
that we have a capacity issue with our
contractors, but um you know, we it's
not like we were stable when we started.
We were in a pretty big hole. And I
think we need to spend these kinds of
dollars uh that the uh the engineer is
talking about to get some of these large
uh deferred maintenance projects off the
books so that we can start to try to get
ahead.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Mr. Esco,
>> Mr. President, through you it's uh what
the mayor said. Uh, I was going to say,
yeah, we're still paying playing
catchup. And, uh, you had a hundred of
our constituents out here in these seats
and you asked each one of them which is
the worst road in Cheyenne, you'd get a
hundred different answers. Yeah, the
ones they live on. It's the worst road
in town. Uh, so I'm on and against the
amendment.
>> Any further discussion on the proposed
amendment? The amendment is to uh delete
number three city street maintenance
project in the amount of $9 million. All
those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All of those opposed. Now
>> uh the proposed amendment fails. Are
there any other amendments?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Mayor, pardon me. You got your
second promotion in a week.
>> Dr.
>> Mr. president.
Again, um going back to my comments
earlier that I do not want to see
recurring funds put into the six penny,
I would um
make a motion to delete the 3.7 million
from the police digital equipment
um and the 1 cent a little over 1
million for fire equipment, I think. Um,
and again, my rationale is again, those
are recurring expenses that should come
out of our general fund. And I think
that we could put
Well, again, if I get a second, I can
tell you where I think we could put it.
>> Um, I want to make sure I have it
correct, Dr. Ry. That's uh item number
four, police digital equipment and
technology. Is that right?
>> Yeah, correct. Let me
>> And the uh number five, fire equipment
and communication replacement project.
We get the right page here.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, we have a motion to uh
eliminate item four and five. Is there a
second?
>> We have a motion and a second. Um
>> Mr. President,
>> Dr. Ren,
>> again, I you know, made my point why I
don't want to see those numbers in
there. I think I would rather put that
money maybe into downtown so it could be
used towards clean and safe which is a
one-time project or used for the um you
know continuation of fifth street do the
do the streetscape 15th street do the
streetscape there um but I think that we
have one-time projects we could put that
money for that the mayor has said we
could take out of the out of the general
fund and pay for those out of the
general general fund. I would rather see
those one-time projects come out of the
six penny and these come out of the
general fund. So,
>> thank you, Dr. Renie. So, we have a
motion in a second. I'll open it up to
the public for discussion.
Public discussion
hearing. None. We'll close that and
we'll bring it up on the dice. Uh Dr.
Aldrich,
>> President Cgrave, uh through you. Um, as
I'm as we were talking about this, I'm
seeing people here in the um chambers
shake their heads no. And um I am going
to be a no vote on this amendment
because while I understand um my
colleague from W 2's um
justification of uh wanting to delete
these um and remove them from this piece
of legislation.
Um I believe that technology one is very
expensive and to replace all of it at
one time for instance on number four the
police digital equipment and technology
project
um
I I think we have some challenges as a
city. We have not done a very good job
in my opinion um over the last 20 to 25
years of um setting aside money each
year um to replace things like this. And
so while we have um sufficient reserves
right now that we could do this from
reserves um and from our general fund um
I don't believe that um our financial
future is so secure that we can make
that assumption that um until no one is
secure until after the legislature goes
home in March. And so I think we need to
really um be cognizant of that. For that
reason, I will be a no vote. And um I
would hope that for public safety
purposes and uh supporting our first
responders in the difficult and
dangerous jobs that they do every single
day that my colleagues will um uh agree
with me and vote no on that amendment.
>> Thank you.
>> Well, Council Moody. Yep.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. Threeu. Um
yeah. Um I want to agree with my
colleague from war 3. I would be a no as
well too. I understand about reoccurring
expenses. It's also to, you know, to
show that we are a community that
supports our uh first responders, both
fire and police, because right now in
this country, unfortunately,
Minneapolis, they're not getting the
support.
>> So, that's why I'll be a nobo because
it's from a psychological aspect and
that's why I think we should vote no.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Renie.
>> Mr. President, not so fast, my friends.
I think we've we've had discussions with
with the mayor about spending almost
First of all, I am not opposed to the
fire department getting this equipment.
Okay. But we've had discussions with the
mayor spending almost that amount of
money to rehab a building downtown for
our clean and safe project. It seems to
me that that money ought to go into the
downtown fund so that we can do the
rehab for that one-time building and
this ought to come out of the general
fund instead of the way we're going to
do it.
>> Dr. Rimmons.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. I have a question
about the equipment for the chief of
police. Um, can you tell us the light uh
lifespan of that equipment?
Mark Francisco Shine Police Chief. Uh
Mr. President through you. The um
equipment that we're talking about here
is purchased on a subscription basis. Um
so that $3.7 million should fund
uh 5 years worth of subscription and
that includes body cameras, incar
cameras, um the latest um electronic
control device commonly called taser. um
along with all the storage and all the
backend software that goes with that. So
um you're looking at about $740,000 a
year were we to to fund it another way,
general fund or whatever. Um so yes,
it's it's not a lifespan. They replace
it as it breaks during the subscription
uh process. um the particular company
we're looking at if they come out with a
newer version, they upgrade us during
that subscription process. So, it's
really um an all-in package deal.
>> So, Mr. Chair, so a followup with that
is I I understand what um Dr. Renie is
talking about with this as a maintenance
rather than a one-time project and and I
agree with that. I also agree that we
need these resources
um in order for you to do the jobs you
need to do. Um is there the potential
that going forward that's something that
we could start building into an annual
budget some way of trying to account for
that every year so that it doesn't
become a maintenance issue at the end of
five years or is that not a possibility?
>> So um my response to that would be is
yes of course that can be done. Um the
the position we're in right now is we um
the body cameras have been replaced.
We're currently using that system. So
this would extend that out. We've
peacemiled some of the cars in. You guys
have voted um on that over the last
couple years. So we really need to do a
one-time completion of all of this to
get everything on the same system
because we're maintaining two right now,
which is workable, but it's not ideal.
Um the only thing I would say um about
using one-time funds is this would be a
contract. It would end um at that point.
We have the option of funding it to
continue um doing it with nothing
requires us to have these things. It's
it's best practices I think everyone
recognizes. Um so we're not trapped with
it at the end of five years. We've we've
met our commitment. the the funding was
there for it and and as we build to that
fifth year then decisions have to be
made about how we go go on with it or
not.
>> Thank you chief uh Dr.
>> uh President Crave through you.
Is there any reason why um this is is it
simply because it has been peacemeal
over the last four or five years since
you became chief um that we haven't uh
started asking for that in our in your
annual budget um building forward
because I think that my colleagues from
W 2 bring up a really good point is that
especially now with all of these crazy
subscription things for everything from
Microsoft Office to obviously body
camera footage and stuff. That's
something that's going to be a recurring
cost that we need to be building into
that budget, recognizing that we need a
big infusion of one-time cash to bring
everything into the same system. And I'm
guessing that there'll be some savings
by not running two systems.
>> Um Mr. President, through you um that is
there would be some savings. Um although
some of the older equipment we actually
own. So it's not um they hadn't
developed that lovely subscription model
that everyone uses now. Um, I would say
I would say there's no good reason we
didn't try and do it all at once other
than we were um being fiscally conscious
and we had planned all along to make
this a um six penny ask and we were
forced into moving quicker because of
the failing system we had. It was just
becoming the body cameras especially
they were becoming untenable and
unreliable and it was it was causing us
problems. So um to refresh your memory,
we we we did that outside of normal
budget process. We kind of kind of had
to do it all of a sudden. So um the
thought that was the thought in our head
that we would go forward. So um we could
certainly um propose that in in a in a
budget budgetary way. Um we just thought
that that this would be a more tenable
way to um do the whole project all at
once and then fund going forward.
Thank you, Chief.
>> Mr. Chairman,
>> um Mr. Mayor,
>> you know, the chief and I have talked
about this for a long time, and we've
been planning to uh to make it a
one-time um ask on the six penny to get
everything going. Um you know, three or
four years ago when we started to uh
look at this, you know, our budgets just
didn't allow for a purchase of this
size. We just didn't have the uh the
reoccurring revenue in his budget. Um
then our body cams failed. We actually
had a case where uh an officer got into
a wrestling match and the and the screen
turned green and the defense attorney
was using that against us saying that
they turned it off. Well, it wasn't that
they turned it off. It's just when you
had a a situation like that, they would
disconnect and turn green and we had to
stop and, you know, and plug this
everything back in. And because of that,
we made the request to uh do the body
cams earlier. But um and that's the
reason, you know, we haven't had in the
budget. We just didn't have the the the
dollar amount. And we've always planned
as the chief and I have been looking
longterm to make this first ask and then
we're we're very hopeful that as our
budget grows and we're in a better
position that we'll be able to start
doing some of these things through the
regular budgetary process.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Council,
>> Mr. President, to you chief. So sooner
you get the money, the sooner you can do
this. So I'm inclined to support the the
amendment.
The amendment is to remove it.
>> Okay. Thank you. Further discussion.
>> Further discussion. Uh, Councilman
White.
>> Thank you. Um, President Cave through
you to the chief.
So, we heard from
engineer Cobb on the previous item. you
know, just because
this is on a ballot and let's say it
gets approved doesn't mean that you have
the money instantaneously.
So where how how does the purchase for
that equipment get funded
because it takes time to collect.
>> Mr. president through you. Um, as as we
did with the radio purchase, uh, we
borrowed our own money, I believe is how
we would we would call that, um, at a 1%
interest rate, knowing that we would
have to then spend a little bit more of
the overage back into it.
>> Thank you, Chief.
>> Further questions? Further questions.
Mr.
>> Mr. President,
Councilman, go ahead and finish up.
>> What I'm saying is if we fund it in the
budget, he can do it. July 1st. If we do
it six penny, it's not going to be till
next year. So, let let's do it in the
budget or or let's do it in a
resolution. Either way, let's do it
sooner.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> uh President Crave through you, I would
just like to point out to my colleagues
and recognizing that uh we had a survey
that was done with uh 17,451
responses of 618 participants. um this
did was an item that was listed um as
34% were likely to vote for this item
and um so I and 20% were somewhat
likely. So, I I it was one of the items
that did receive some of the most
support from our um constituents. And uh
again, I would say that it's one of
those statutory things and whether we
pay for it um through the six penny or
we pay for it out of our general
reserves, we need to do it.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldrich. Further
comments?
Further comments. The uh proposed
amendment is to eliminate item eliminate
item number four, police digital
equipment and technology and item number
five, fire equipment in a communication
replacement project.
All of those in favor signify by saying
I.
>> I
all those opposed.
>> No.
>> Uh that proposed amend uh substitute
fails.
>> Mr. Mr. Mr. Chairman, can I just have a
tally of who voted yes, please?
>> Uh,
>> thank you,
>> Dr. Renie and Councilman Esel.
>> Um, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Oh, are there uh are there other
proposed
uh substitutes or amendments to the
>> I'm I'm done, Mr. President.
>> Okay, Dr. Aldrich. Um, President Crave,
I would like to um
see number seven um $4 million for the
Reed Avenue corridor for the downtown
improvement projects um be replaced with
um the the Reed Avenue Pro corridor
project. Um I and I'll make a motion
then I'll explain it after I get a
second.
>> Second. Okay, we have a motion to
eliminate uh eliminate the item number
seven and replace it with $4 million for
the Reed Avenue project. Uh Dr.
Aldridge,
>> uh President Crave, my reasoning for
doing this is that we have invested a
lot of money in the downtown um area out
of the last six penny ballot. And I
think um our director of community wreck
and events um Jason Sanchez does an
amazing job with stretching those
dollars. And while I recognize that that
is the heart of our community and there
is still work to be done there, um I
also recognize that we have um a group
of people on the Reed Avenue corridor
that um have been waiting um to have
some sort of um action quite honestly
taken over on the Reed Avenue corridor.
A lot of the funding that was raised
through a six penny ballot um two times
ago has been uh spent on um some very
unsuccessful plans and consultants and
some very successful plans and
consultants. Um but the planning stage
is over. um you know it's time to move
from planning to action and I think that
our uh residents on the Reed Avenue
corridor and our business owners and the
people who have invested personally
millions of dollars in that area um
while this preceded my time on the
council they um have an expectation that
we meet that commitment to them. Um, so
for that reason, I'm I would like to see
us replace the downtown improvement
project um on the sixpity ballot um for
this particular ballot and this
particular ask uh for one time with a
Reed Avenue corridor versus the downtown
improvement project.
>> All right, we have a motion and a
second. I'll open it up to the public
for discussion.
Discussion. Mr. Rididgeway.
Thank you.
>> Uh Mr. President, just to to want to uh
reaffirm my previous comments is one is
there's only a a 30% I believe
commitment from the railroad at this
time. uh you're looking at uh
I guess soil soil testing could be done
in results, but I think that you're
looking at using a smart taxpayer money
and I don't think it would be until you
get some final answers on a lot of those
items, especially with the railroad only
being in 30%.
uh if the soil's contaminated, you're
going to be spending millions of dollars
on remediation and you don't know what's
in there yet. So, I don't uh as a voter,
I would not support that.
Thank you, Mr. Rididgeway. Other uh
comments from the public?
Anyone else? Jennifer, anyone online?
No. All right, we will close public
comment. We'll bring it back up on the
DAS. Um,
let's start at this end. Dr. Rimmons.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Um, so a couple
of questions. First question is, what
would we be doing with that $4 million?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> I thank you, President Crave. Um, I
believe that um, Engineer Cobb has a um,
a budget type plan that we could utilize
funds for to initiate what I believe is
a park at the north end of that and to
help move the process along with the
railroad. My understanding is that we
are uh have been working with the
railroad and have a we're closer in
agreement to the rail with the railroad
now than we've ever been and to stop the
momentum at this point could change the
trajectory of that project etern
forever. But perhaps Mr. Cobb or Mr.
Labbornne the chairman of that committee
could answer that.
>> Director Cobb
what would you do with the $4 million?
Um, President Crave through you, I
guess, to the council in general. Um,
I've been looking at this um,
wholeheartedly for the last month and a
half um, in quite detail. And as the
mayor had indicated in his presentation,
I presented to him sort of a
countermeasure offer of what I think we
could do. And I think what we could do
is what we promised. I think we can have
a a pedestrian corridor on the east side
with with amenities. And what I what
I've sort of done is I looked at this as
I what what skipped out of what was out
of the 14 million that they looked at
originally is not doing right now the
the area that would be their service
road. So I eliminated the railroad
service road from consideration at this
point. They they eventually want us to
do something with that but it wouldn't
be part of this. So, I'm looking at the
prominade, the pedestrian prominade on
the east side plus some form of what the
park was that they're showing. Not in
the not to the degree of amenities that
we're showing. It's going to be basic
amenities. And I budgeted about a
million for amenities and the remainder
would be for storm sewer and um and and
pedestrian improvements. And then of
course I'm hoping that I can use some of
the storm water impact fee to help
alleviate some of the drainage that I
could pay for from that. So that is my
hope. Um or the drainage money that we
get from the fifth penny. So with the
combination of those sorts, I I
indicated the mayor that I thought I
needed about 5 million to do that.
>> Dr. Thank you, Mr. Chair. So I
personally I'm not comfortable with a
swag kind of let's do about 4 million.
We don't really know what exactly we
would do with it. Um and my concern
while I totally support that area and
the people that are down there and
respect all of the work that they've
done and continue to do. Um, I think
that it's I don't like the idea that
we're not finishing what we're starting.
And I think that looks really bad for a
taxpayer, for a citizen, for you know,
those of us in this room. And unless we
have very clear
um
agreements with the railroad, I agree
with Mr. Ridgeway that the idea of
saying we think they'll let us do this
just does not sit well with me. So I
would have concerns about going forward
with this.
>> Thank you. Uh Council Wolf.
>> Um thank you Mr. President through you.
Um
first of all speaking in defense uh well
let me just say this. speaking on and
against the amendment. Um, first in
defense of the downtown money and this
actually addresses Mr. Rididgeway. Thank
you for your comments. And we need to
make clear what that money is for. That
money is for three things. It's for
sidewalks and gutter. It's for
renovation of the depot railroad museum.
And it's for uh Mr. Sanchez, Director
Sanchez's,
uh, needs a space to store all the trash
and recycling bins. Um, and all of those
are very useful investments in the
downtown.
Um, second point, um, is that I've spent
more time on the Reed Avenue project,
uh, in the last, uh, two months, um,
than just about anything else I've done.
Uh, and I've met, uh, over at Westpies,
uh, several times uh, with the, uh, Mr.
Tubner who owns Warehouse 21, with the
Westpies themselves. I've talked to the
people who were up and down that
corridor spent u and I thank director um
Cobb for his time on this. The reality
is I started out including the Reed
Avenue project in my six penny analysis
and I as time went on I came to the
conclusion it's simply not ready for a
six penny vote. Um, I've spent
considerable time obviously talking with
Councilman Lebornne about this. It's a
word one project. I think the project is
very important, but there remain some
critical issues um that uh we need to
work out with the railroad. That project
proposes because of the railroad's
insistence that we close four streets.
that actually is problematic for uh some
of the existing business owners there.
We need to make an investment there.
I've sat down with Mr. Tubner at a
length, given him copies of the plans,
gone over uh the issues with him. I
think he understands why it's not an
ideal six penny project because at this
point we have nothing to show for it
except a lot of work and a lot of work
on plans. We have a 30% plan. We hope to
go to a 65% plan. Um, but I'm um all of
that taking into account both the
interests I think in supporting the
downtown investment and the status of
this project. And that's not a criticism
of anybody because Mr. Cobb has worked
extraordinarily hard on this, but um I
would vote no on the amendment. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Councilman Moody.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. hear you.
Yeah, I want to uh also uh I'll be in no
vote and well my colleague from war once
said absolutely uh the museum does need
to be refurbished. I was in there less
than 30 days ago. It needs new carpet
badly. That's probably one of the things
that needs to be replaced almost
immediately. And then um our new vice
president has shown me around downtown
there are a lot of cracks in our
sidewalks. There are curbs that are in
disrepair.
Just remember when people visit our
town, especially during the summer
months, that is what they see first. We
got to fix those basics and constituents
want the basics fixed. So, while I
appreciate the amendment, I will be a no
vote on it. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Um, Councilman Esel.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. through you on
the subject of the contamination,
wouldn't it be narrowed down to just the
track area? Because during my time,
which goes back to 1979 of working on
the railroad, that track mostly carried
the rock for the bedding of the track,
the ballast. Uh so the locomotives
um
hardly any diesel would escape
off the track into the area where where
you're talking about the pedestrian
walkways.
>> President Crave through you to council
and ESL. So I've done a really poor job
tonight of speaking. So I will say to
you this the conversation I just had
today with the FRA environmental
representative which I should have
answered this with Mr. Ridgeway earlier.
So I asked her a direct question cuz I
said what would we expect is having
issues in this particular corridor given
the fact what I just said. You said I
repeated the same thing that you said
and she said there is there they do not
have a concern. She's more concerned
about cultural resources. So I can say
to you what I mean by that is we have
sighting tracks that have have track
stamps on them from 1885.
So it's more about cultural resources
than actual contamination. So those
siding tracks that go into the side
buildings, they have this old track that
belongs to the BNSF um that we're going
to have to figure out how we deal with
those cultural resources. But
environmentally, she didn't have many
concerns at all. She said that it would
be very little contamination would be
expected, but she said she won't say
that until we know for sure we have to
do the process. But again, from their
standpoint, that's where they stood.
>> Mr. president. That's why I would
support this amendment to show a
commitment to the west edge. I mean,
it's one part of the city that's left
out and it's been on six penny
previously.
So, it shows the public we're giving up.
We're stopping in the middle. We have to
show something.
I support the amendment.
>> Thank you. Um, Councilman White,
anything?
>> Yes, sir. Um, President C. Grave through
you. I'll be supporting the amendment as
well. Um, for the reasons Mr. Escoel
just stated and and and Dr. Aldridge, I
think that to just
do a full stop at this present time
would really
uh hurt the momentum that that we've
gained just in the last six, seven
months. We've made more progress in the
last six, seven months than we have in
the last five, six years. Um, so I I
want to see that continue.
>> Dr. Aldridge, anything else?
>> Uh, President Crave, I would just I I
had a couple of questions for uh Mr.
Cobb. One is um if we were to if we
don't have funding in this six penny
ballot for this project
um
do you anticipate being able to find
that funding anywhere other than the
general reserves or the general fund?
>> Director
>> President Crave through you to Dr.
Aldrich. No, ma'am.
>> Do we have enough pres three? Do we have
enough money left from the original six
penny ballot on this? Um how much do we
have left approximately and and what are
the plans for that funding?
>> President Crave through you to Dr.
Aldridge. Right now, ma'am, there's
approximately 2.2 million. Um the only
thing that we have not allocated yet is
our match to the FRA, which is the
875,000.
So, some of that is going to have to
come out of of that as well. and no
other at this point that has been
dedicated to anything at this particular
juncture. Ma'am,
>> and a follow-up question, council member
Grave, um when we are dealing with the
railroad, uh I because I think we've
made significant progress there if we um
don't show continuing support for this
project. Um, do you believe that we'll
be able to continue to make because
we're having to pay for these steps with
the railroad is my understanding as
well. Will we be able to um make
continuous u progress with the railroad
or are we going to lose ground and I've
been I've heard I don't know if this is
accurate. Please correct me if I'm wrong
that we may never get back to this point
again because they will not want to
waste their time retreading old ground
five or six or 10 or 15 years from now.
Director C,
>> President Cra through you to Dr.
Aldridge that that questions I I
obviously can't answer specifically to
your to your question, but I I can say
to you I I
obviously the momentum is the
relationships we've established keeping
and progressing forward with the
relationships that we have I think is
important. So I think any change in that
as as their staff has been consistent
and ours as well which before that both
on both sides of the the track so to
speak we're changing constantly that
didn't help at all. So I think from
uniformity standpoint with keeping those
relationships that we have and keeping
that momentum forward is going to help
that the the project move forward very
quickly. Um I I I I think the statement
about the 30% is as I'd indicated in
several occasions. Um I I I don't I
don't think that's they've approved a
30% plan, but we submitted the entire
plan. So the entire plan they're in
support of other than items that we have
to change that related to sight distance
near the crossings, landscaping elements
they don't want, you know, some of the
signage we have to add. Those are just
elements, but they've agreed in
principle to the entire plan. I think
that needs to be understood to
everybody. They have they they they've
made their agreement with us. They um
they've committed to the 22905 which is
basically what says the crossing
elimination grant they're in support of.
They're in support of the project as a
whole. So they they are there. Do I have
something officially in writing for
because now we have to move to a second
agreement. We have the PE agreement that
I talk about all the time which is
preliminary engineering. We have a
second document which um at that time I
think was presented to the council and
and the only one that I don't think was
here was Mr. Wolf. Um we have a second
document that we have to come in and
again pay them for for the construction
component because they do some of the
inspection. We have to pay for the
signal equipment that gets removed
because they do that work. So but again
they are in support of the project 100%.
They're all in. They've seen everything
now. Um I hope that answers your
question.
Dr. Aldrich,
>> the $4 million um then that um you had
talked with us about at the work
session. Um I just want to make sure
that I understand it would it's the
prominade along the east side and would
that include and the the park at the
north end which which would not have all
the bells and whistles that we would
like it to have but it would uh show
that form of commitment um to those West
Edge um property owners. And um then
would that al then at that and it does
not include uh having at that $4 million
could be spent without having to close
the four uh streets at this time um on
this project or the prominade require
the four streets to be closed.
>> Director President Cra you to Dr.
Aldridge. So we have to look at these as
even though it's one project we have to
look at them as two. So we have the FRA
grant which promises the foreclosures
and then we have the prominade project
which is basically read as a proper. So
you we have another contract that you'll
see in front of you with with the
consultant that we currently have. We're
going to have to add roughly $200,000 to
their contract which is going to pay be
paid out of the FRA portion for the
design of the closures themselves for
the components that weren't included in
the original reed project. Okay. So, I'm
I think I've lost myself in my own
words, but the four the four million the
four million boy I am really struggling.
I didn't get any sleep last night. I
should have went to bed a little
earlier. Um the 4 million would be yes
for the prominade the features that we
talked about and I have to clarify my
further statement again. I'm not doing a
very good job of speaking tonight which
is not usually my forte but I usually do
a better job. the entire project. We're
looking at their concept of this
project, but it's removing some of the
elements that like they were looking at
cooling towers and giant o overhead like
an old an old uh I guess it was an
observation tower for a train. We're not
including those elements. There'll be
basic amenities for benches and planters
and and some aesthetic features, but the
only thing that would be eliminated are
some of those larger architectural
elements that were discussed with this
this group with um uh at some of the
work sessions that were previously done.
Those elements could be added at a
future date, but we're removing those
big huge architectural components right
now just to get the project in in the
prominade that we talked about. Does
that answer your question? Yes, I just
had one more question and we actually
have received the grant for those
closings.
>> President Crave through you to Dr.
Aldridge. We have received the grant.
The grant paperwork itself will be
closing that documentation out at the
end of February. We have constant
monthly meetings with the FRA, but the
agreement isn't official yet, but we're
working on that right now. And it
roughly 3.7 million total.
>> Thank you.
>> We'll go down here. Dr. Simmons.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. So just for
clarification, it does or does not
include closing the four streets.
>> President Crave through you to Dr.
Emmens. The $4 million does not include
the closures. This is in addition to the
3.7 million that would be invested on
the closures themselves with the FRA
grant and the $875,000
match of the city.
>> U Mr. President, so with the 2.2 2
million that we still have left. We
could continue some efforts to show that
we are continuing to work with them to
show good faith by using those funds.
Would that not be correct?
>> Director C.
>> President Cra through you to Dr. Emmens.
Could you clarify what you mean by what
what they would be spent for? Ma'am,
>> uh Mr. President, I don't know what they
would be spent for, but you just said we
have $2.2 2 million left from the
original six penny. So we will continue
to spend that money. Correct.
>> President C. Grave through you to Dr.
Emmens. Yes, ma'am. As needed. As as
needed. Again, those are unencumbered
funds. So, some of that would be the
875,000 I talked about for the grant
match and then whatever we would need
moving forward. If we choose once the
project as I've said before the design
the complete design has to be approved
by the railroad and then once that
design is approved by the railroad
officially the 100% then we can phase
the project any way that we want to
>> Mr. President. So we would not be
completely stopping I mean they're still
going to be able to see progress because
we've got the $2.2 million that we can
still be completing activities with.
President Crrave through you to Dr. Dr.
Emmens. Dr. Emmens. So, anything on the
corridor itself, I cannot do until we
receive the full 100% approval from the
railroad. I could work on the park area
to the north. Yes, I'm continuing to
work, but what seeing it on the ground,
that's for interpretation, right? The
only spot that I can work in would be
the triangle area that we have full
control over. I won't be able to work on
any other any of the other stuff until
we get full approval
>> which is the construction drawings.
>> So by working on the triangle area we
would still be showing the folks in that
area that we are committed to moving
forward with the project.
>> Director C
>> President Crave threw you to Dr. Emmens.
Yes ma'am. And what I I but I want to
answer your question though because I
did do a full estimate on that and the
consultant came back at 5 million for
the triangle. Okay. I redid it with my
folks in the 1% construction department
and and with some of my staff came in at
around 2.1 million. So that's what's
left. What we think the triangle would
be based on the current design that it
had excluding that observation tower
that they were showing earlier.
>> One more question.
So, with the 2.2 million, um, if we if
we had,
um, for instance, if we were to split
the downtown and the reed,
then you could have potentially $4
million.
>> No. Okay.
>> Because you
>> I think the secret for you to, Dr.
Emmens. Yes, ma'am. But again, the
875,000 I'm still missing. That's the
2.2 million does not include the 875
match for the FRA grant because it's not
been fully executed. So, there's a bit
of a deficit, but yes, overall. Yes,
ma'am.
>> Thank you,
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you, uh, Mr. President, through
you. Um, let's clear up a few things
here. Um,
number one,
um,
we just got a memo from Director Cobb
for our discussions tomorrow.
That memo makes no reference at all to
doing the triangle, not spending one
dime on that, even though we have $2.2
million left from the 2017
authorization.
And the reason for that, I believe, is a
kind of well-reasoned
decision by the mayor and his chief of
staff that were not ready to do that. So
that's sort of point number one is and
that this 2.2 is there. The whole
question about this goes to two issues.
Number one, the issue that I have
written the entire council about is that
we cannot and should not consider the
six penny
except in the context of how we use our
reserves and we never we haven't had
that conversation. We're going to start
that tomorrow because I want to make it
really clear to this assembled group
that I support the Reed Avenue project.
I think it is an essential undertaking
for the city. What I don't support is
both taking this money out of the
downtown investment
and
putting it into the reserve into the
Reed Avenue project in some nebulous way
because we're going to have a real hard
time selling that to the public because
they're going to ask us, you've been at
this now for eight years and you have
nothing to show for it. And that's
that's not a correct understanding of
all the things that have gone on. We owe
and have made promises to the Reed
Avenue
merchants, the people who made the
investment here, and I want to see us
complete that. And the Reed Avenue is an
critical connection into the 15th Street
project into the development of the pump
house. And I think actually to give the
mayor a credit, he has plans for how all
that should work. So when we talk
tomorrow night, I'm going to ask us to
consider making a commitment of reserves
of like $5 million to the Reed Avenue
project, but I don't think it belongs on
the sixth penny. Thank you, Mr.
President.
>> Thank you, Dr. Anything else? Okay.
Okay. Councilman Esco.
>> Uh, Mr. President, uh,
I just want to kind of remind everybody
on Monday night what one of the, uh,
owners of property on Reed Avenue
corridor had said when we approved that
liquor license
and just the amount of people that were
were down here and also how long it
would take for us to make this money. uh
after the ballot and uh what the mayor
said, we're about 18 months out with the
railroad on getting permission.
I I believe that will happen. Uh
and I think the timing of when we get
the money and timing of when the the
railroad
is fully committed should all sink
whether we do it this way or tomorrow.
uh the way uh my colleague from Ward One
has said uh I think we could show the
commitment one way or another and I'll
support the amendment.
>> Anyone else? Else
>> Mr. Chairman, thank you through you. Um
let me let me kind of make one other
point and that goes to this street
closure.
One of the concerns we have is that if
we proceed under the FRA grant that they
will demand that we close the streets
and these streets are 17th, 18th and
21st. and understand that the demand the
railroad is making on us is we not only
close them to vehicular traffic, we
close them to pedestrian traffic as
well.
That issue is of great concern to
everybody on the Reed Avenue corridor
and to people who use those arteries to
get back and forth to Snider. and we
have a 100 unit apartment complex coming
online
that may change the issues there
dramatically in terms of traffic traffic
demand. Um, so I think it is it is just
and and the other point to understand is
that what's being proposed in the Reed
Avenue project only benefits
the people on the east side
doesn't benefit at all. And I heard and
had a long conversation yesterday with
the man who owns On the Spot Glass,
which is on the the west side of the uh
uh 21st Street, and he's he doesn't
think that doing these improvements on
the east side is going to benefit him at
all. And he makes a very uh sort of
casual comment about there are no
pedestrians over here.
But he doesn't, I think, like the idea
of closing the streets. And we
have to get to a resolution of that. And
that's going to involve and going to
have to involve the mayor, director
Cobb, and some other key officials to
see if we can't get to a resolution that
actually satisfies all the interests.
So, I think we're doing absolutely the
right thing by taking this off the six
penny ballot, committing reserves in a
way through council action or through
the budget so that the people on Reed
Avenue, the investors that we have
promised that we will work on and um so
I would um I guess I'd call for the
question, Mr.
information first.
>> Well, Mr.
>> Dr. Ren,
>> Mr. President, I just wanted to My
understanding was the railroad is now
asking for four streets to be closed,
not three. So, I just wanted to make
sure we had accurate information. Can
Can that be addressed?
>> Dr. Renie, they're closing Deming.
That's the fourth street, but Deming
doesn't affect anybody. It's just a
little tiny
>> connection off of that
>> point of order have to go through chair.
>> Let's let's get it from director cop.
How many streets are we closing?
>> President's secret through to the
council. So there are four total three
that lie on the corridor 17th 18th 21st
on the corridor itself and then Dylan
Avenue which is up by the board of
public utilities just south of the
building. Sir,
>> thank you Mr. President.
>> Point of point of information
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> President Crave. Um my understanding is
that we have already a agreed or the
finance committee has already voted to
support the grant that is is it called
the TFR grant. So whether we approve
that or not that ship has kind of sailed
is my understanding unless we return the
funds or reject the funds.
>> Director Co
to Dr. Aldridge. Yes ma'am. We've
initially done that. Um that the final
agreement will be circulated to the
council though.
Mr. Secret, I might do a point of
information.
>> Yes, Mr.
>> Just quick, sir. Thank you. Um,
we're talking about how how can we do
this the fastest and uh we're going to
vote on this next um
next August and it's going to take a
while for us to start collecting the
money and then the money is going to
come in. We're going to get it at the
prat a share, you know, so if we get
five projects passed, it's going to get
its its section of that that money or
that its percentage of that money. So,
it's going to take a while for us to be
able to collect enough money to be able
to do this. So, my thought was that um
I'm very supportive of this, but we
actually should be able to do it faster
by using the money out of reserves
because as soon as the 18 months are up
and we get permission from the the
railroad to do this project. All it
takes is six members of this governing
body to vote for the um uh whatever the
contract is that comes out of it. We
should be able to do this a lot quicker
paying for it out of our own funds than
waiting for the six penny sales tax to
be collected. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Councilman Labour.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Um, first of
all, I'd like to compliment Mr. Cobb for
a very arduous and uh
difficult uh dealings with the railroad,
which we probably don't understand as
well as people who deal with the
railroad all the time. And years ago
when this ballot question went before
the voters in 2017,
it was not properly prepared.
But the commitment was made and uh those
individuals whether they're right on the
corridor or couple blocks away or in
this on this side of town uh saw that
opportunity and invested. And I also
want to thank all my colleagues for the
discussion we're having here tonight.
It's uh it's a difficult one. It's hard
to grasp. I think we can uh continue
here and come to more clarity about it.
One of the things I want to emphasize is
those closures sound really bad.
When you come to understand them better,
the number of vehicles that use them and
where they are, you come to understand
that that safety consideration for the
railroad is equally a safety
consideration for us and the people who
are there. This is going to change uh
that neighborhood forever. It's going to
make a big difference. And so I I
glad to have this discussion whether we
do it one way or whether we do it the
other way. And certainly I can I can
tell uh all my colleagues this that uh
speaking in favor of a resolution
uh or an amendment that would
uh very much change uh the funding of
our uh curb gutter sidewalk and
infrastructure throughout the downtown
is kind of a
difficult one for me. Uh, I've been
working on that for a long time, but I
think we can uh find some ways to make
this happen, and this is a good way to
make it happen. So, I speak in favor of
uh this amendment, and I really look
forward to
having more communication with everyone,
investors, the neighborhood,
the council people, because Mr. Cobb has
quite a story to tell and the most
important part of that story is his 100%
agreement that this
30% design with the railroad is the
initial step
that will take us where we need to go
and it didn't happen before. A lot of
lot of money and expertise was invested
in it. So, um I believe that this is uh
probably uh
the best way. I'm not sure it's the only
way. We're going to see this through one
way or the other. I look forward to
doing my best as chairman of the Reed
Avenue steering committee to be
communicating with everyone
and being able to answer those specific
questions in a different type of a
meeting than we're having here tonight.
But I appreciate the consideration. I
appreciate what uh Mr. Cobb has done and
I appreciate what uh the investors have
have done and this and the people who
have committed to what really is a very
difficult but very contemporary and
important project. So again, I I speak
in favor of this and I look forward to
um
whichever way the cards fall, we're
going to see this through. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Lever. Back to Aldridge.
>> Uh, President Crave through you. I would
just remind my colleagues that um if we
can do the Reed Avenue corridor through
our general reserves, we can surely do
the downtown improvements uh that are
suggested in this list uh through that
mechanism as well. And I think that um
this is really important to include the
Reed Avenue corridor in place of the
downtown improvements projects on the
six penny ballot um to as a
reaffirmation of our commitment to those
uh Reed Avenue corridor um constituents
and folks um in the on the west edge.
and um that I would just
ask you to think about the optics of uh
support um in this manner. Thank you.
>> Further discussion, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. President, um
in regard to my um colleagues comments,
I would flip that exactly the opposite
also. I mean, it's a it's this is a
difficult situation because we have been
very adamant to the downtown businesses
who have shown up repeatedly in this
room asking us over and over why we
haven't fixed their sidewalks, why their
curbs are broken up. I mean, many of you
have talked about how bad or uh shape
our streets are in. And I worry that
when you're talking about optics, it's
going to be as bad, if not worse, by
saying to those folks who have made the
effort to be here and have um
you know, kind of beat us up on this
that we're not taking care of them. So,
I mean, if we're looking at optics, it's
going to go both ways. President Crave,
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Um, thank you for that comment and I
understand what my colleague is saying.
However,
um, I if when we talk about, you know,
the concern about doing um, ongoing
maintenance uh, with six penny money,
when I look at this list of downtown
improvements, they're really quite
honestly, I'm not so sure that they're
really improvements. Uh, I mean, they're
improvements, but they're not new
improvements. They are really
maintenance and facilities. Uh the Jack
Spiker parking garage elevator needs
replaced. That's maintenance issue. The
Cheyen depot museum needs a renovation.
A lot of that has to do with maintenance
issues and a refurbishing. The
construction of enclosed storage areas
is a new piece, but curbon sidewalk
improvements or repairs, again,
maintenance. So, um it's Yeah. Six of
one, half dozen of another.
>> Thank you. Further discussion.
Further discussion.
The uh proposed amendment is to
eliminate downtown improvement projects
and replace it with the Reed Avenue
project.
All of those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Can I see the hands of of the eyes? We
have one, two, three, four. Those
opposed?
>> No.
>> No. Uh the I will be a no vote. This um
proposed amendment fails. Are there
other um changes the council is
interested in?
All right. Maybe we're ready for a final
vote. Uh if you'll allow me, I have one
question, Mr. Mayor. Um,
if this is approved, is this language in
each one of these exactly what the
ballot is going to say or are there
going to be
modifications to the ballot language? Do
we know yet?
>> Mr. President, to you I'm not positive
that this is exact language. Um, I think
we want to bring our committee together
here. Um, I think it's next Wednesday.
We'll start working on the language. Um
probably need to sit down with uh Mr.
Brody again just to make sure. We put
this together pretty quickly to get it
before you. Um I don't want to commit to
that. I think we probably need to look
at just a little bit, but I think the
language I mean the asks are the same.
We might change the language slightly as
describing the projects.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Appreciate that,
>> Mr. President. Council Leborn.
>> Well, I think that's a good point and I
think that probably a little word
smithing there might be in order.
Certainly when we're talking about how
those are going to be grouped with the
county and the rural communities, um I I
think that's quite correct. Um I don't
think there's going to be any major
changes, but um that ballot language is
real important. And if we if there I
certainly have a couple things here I'd
like to talk about as we proceed here,
but not these aren't substantive
changes. These are uh descriptions and I
think that uh probably we could do a
little bit of uh effort there but it's
not going to change the amounts and the
purposes. Thank you. Uh Dr.
>> President Crave, I did have a question
also about the groupings. Um thinking
about how those were grouped last time.
Um,
is it correct in um or are you thinking
that the municipal building will be a
standalone project?
>> Mr. President, through you. Yes, ma'am.
I think they'll do some groupings of uh
public safety, some groupings of
infrastructure, and then other projects
that don't really fit well into those
will probably end up being standalone. I
would anticipate Johnson Pool, the fire
station, and the municipal building
would definitely uh be standalone
projects.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mr. President,
>> Dr. Ren,
>> just to confirm that in my discussions
with Commissioner Malm, they have a
major remodel, I think, of the jail
scheduled. Also, both that project and
um the city building will be standalone
projects.
>> Thank you, Dr. Alers.
>> Question um for Councilman Renie,
Chairman Crave. Are you saying that they
would each stand alone on their own or
they would be combined as renovation and
remodeling projects?
>> They would stand alone on their own. So
our city project would be separate from
the county project.
>> Correct.
>> Thank you.
>> Further discussion. Further discussion.
Anyone?
>> Or are we ready for a final vote? All of
those in favor of the resolution signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
Uh Dr. Renie is a no. Uh the resolution
passes. The recommendation for the next
city council meeting, I'm not sure of
the date, um will be to approve. Thank
you very much. I appreciate all your
efforts. We'll see you tomorrow night.
>> Thank you everyone. Thank you guys.